<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Quantitative Rhetoric</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://quantitativerhetoric.com/</id><updated>2018-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - June 2018</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-june-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2018-07-07:monthly-rental-report-june-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;WARNING&lt;/em&gt; - Due to last month's methodology change, I can no longer track studio pricing. Onwards!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;June Real Estate Happenings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been six months since the City of Vancouver adopted a ten year housing plan. As a reminder, the plan's aim is to create 72,000 new homes affordable to local incomes by 2028. In June, the city released the first &lt;a href="http://council.vancouver.ca/20180619/documents/rr1a.pdf"&gt;status report&lt;/a&gt; on progress so far. How are we doing? I'll spare you the 200+ pages of suspense - we're on track! The city approved 7, 141 new units in 2017, falling just a hair short of their annual target of 7, 200. I might just be a worry wart but 2017 was a banner year for housing, and I'd be impressed if CoV could stay the course for the coming decade. Here's a snapshot of the approvals: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/2017-housing-approvals-CoV.png" /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: Affordable Housing Delivery and Financial Strategy and Annual Progress Report and Housing Vancouver Data Book&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CoV approvals are overweight on condos (128%), and supportive housing (142%), but severely lagging on PBRs (41%), and townhomes (38%). To the city's credit, these shortfalls were called out and will hopefully be addressed in 2018.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In tangentally related news, the government of BC released a &lt;a href="https://news.gov.bc.ca/files/German_Gaming_Final_Report.pdf"&gt;bombshell report&lt;/a&gt; on money laundering. This study was backed by David Eby and details how criminal money is flooding into our economy. Peter German, the report's author, conservatively estimates that at least $100M has been laundered in BC in the last decade. While, the report doesn't attempt to detail the flow of dirty money, it does highlight real estate as a likely destination for these funds. The report was such a hit that there will be a sequel. The target? &lt;a href="https://www.thestar.com/vancouver/2018/06/28/real-estate-investigation-is-next-for-author-of-bc-casino-money-laundering-report.html"&gt;BC's real estate sector&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually we focus on rentals here, but let's talk about sales for a minute. Real estate sales and rental markets should move in opposite directions because they are alternative uses for the same unit. In a rapidly appreciating market, investors can afford to keep a unit empty while the value balloons. However, flat prices mean they are &lt;a href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/case-studies-in-renting-versus-buying.html"&gt;bleeding cash through interest, maintenance and taxes&lt;/a&gt; every month. Thanks to Steve Saretsky, we have some numbers from behind the shroud of MLS secrecy. Last month, condo sales dropped ~30% to match 2012 lows, and detached homes haven't seen this sort of sales drought since 1991. Don't expect prices to fall off a cliff though, because RE prices can be incredibly sticky. Without a catalyst, recent buyers will likely sit pat for the next few years of 0% growth rather than sell at a loss. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;June Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prices&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1900 (-2.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2612.50 (-3.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3000 (-5.3%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rental prices are finally dropping in the face of consistently higher volumes. Last month, we discussed how prices have been flat since March. They seem to have finally succumbed to the economic gravity of higher supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June there was a 15% drop in the number of listings. This matches last year's pattern of unit volumes dropping between May and June. I guess everyone wants to come here for the summer. The 3 month trend continues to move upwards, and there was a +15% YoY change compared to June last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year-Over-Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the latest drop in prices, we are no longer seeing large YoY gains. These price increases are actually in line with inflation, and slightly below the maximum raise that landlords are entitled to by the province. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2018&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1850&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1900&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%2.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2550&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2612&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%2.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2910&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/volumes-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/volumes-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/volumes-3.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - May 2018</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-may-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2018-06-07:monthly-rental-report-may-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WARNING - METHODOLOGY CHANGE&lt;/strong&gt;: The way I gather rental listings had to be modified in mid-May for technical reasons. There may be a small discrepancy in the rental volume. A comparison of the first 14 days of April to May, where the methodology matches, suggests that the effect is minor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May Housing News&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our provincial government worked overtime in May. They updated the rules protecting renters and started collecting information on presale assignments for taxation purposes. In contrast, nothing much happened on the municipal and national front. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BC government &lt;a href="https://www2.gov.bc.ca/gov/content/housing-tenancy/residential-tenancies/changes-to-tenancy-laws"&gt;amended the Residential Tenancy Act&lt;/a&gt; giving tenants more protection. This change provides a measure of security for renters, and discourages some scummy landlording behaviour. The result is another factor weighing down buyer demand. Let me explain. Anecdotally, I often hear people buying for fear of eviction. The BC government seems to have noticed and really brought the hammer down with two big changes. First, wrongful evictions will now cost &lt;em&gt;a year's worth&lt;/em&gt; of compensation instead of 2 months. Second, landlords must now provide 4 months of notice instead of 2 for a legal eviction. A landlord will probably think twice before trying to boot a tenant to close the gap to market rents. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our government recently passed Bill 25, the Real Estate Development Marketing Amendment Act. This bill didn't get as much coverage in the media but it requires that developers track assignment transactions and make them available to our government. Like ticket scalping, people are purchasing pre-sale units without any intention of owning it. Instead, they wait for the price to go up and flips contract to purchase that unit. Previously, this activity was done "off-the-books" resulting in hundreds of thousands of dollars in tax-free gains. The ways to make a quick buck off of RE are getting plugged one by one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over in Ottawa, Justin Trudeau was too busy buying us a pipeline to do much for housing. I've always wanted to be 1/36,000,000th an oil baron. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Vancouver was too embroiled in political jockeying for the upcoming mayoral election. Ken Sim ended up winning the nomination for NPA. Congrats Ken! So, everyone ready for sim-city? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, enough joking around. Time to hit those numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prices&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1700 (+.59%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1952 (+.13%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2800 (+0.0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3170 (5.8%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to strong volume growth, prices have flatlined since March for most unit types. 3BRs seem to have gone up in both price in volume. These larger units saw a a marked increase $3170, which is well above prices we've seen previously. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to see volume growth in rental listings. Vancouver saw 15% more listings between April 2018 and May 2018. I added a new chart showing that volume growth in the 1BR and 2BR segment is incredibly strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year-Over-Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, we are observing the structural shift in the rental market prices. While rents for a particular unit can only go up at inflation + 2%, we are seeing outsized increases in the turnover rent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YoY statistics cannot be read off the graph due to the methodology change mentioned above. I estimated YoY change using just the first 15 days of each month, an apples-to-apples comparison. Rental volumes were up 13% YoY in the first half of the month. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2018&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1700&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%6.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1850&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1952&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%5.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2700&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%8.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2825&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3170&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%12.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/may-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/volumes-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/may-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/volumes-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/may-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/volumes-3.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/may-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/may-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - April 2018</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-april-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-05-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2018-05-05:monthly-rental-report-april-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;April was a hot month for housing news. I'll just briefly summarize here with some links. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actions taken by  government and activists to curb the housing crisis is drawing some pretty strong reaction from home owners. A particular flashpoint is the "school tax" on $3M+ homes. This tax is calculated on the portion of the home value assessed above $3M. There are protesters who cite that they cannot afford to pay such a tax. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a quote from the mayor of West Vancouver, "There are an awful lot of people that might have paid $30,000 or $40,000 for their house that’s now worth $4 million or $5 million. They’re not wealthy people." In what world is having $4 million not wealthy? I'd just like to point out that at .20%, the proceeds of selling the home could pay for the tax for &lt;em&gt;500 years&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Housing News&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REBGV released &lt;a href="https://www.rebgv.org/monthly-reports/april-2018"&gt;sales stats&lt;/a&gt; for April and transaction volumes are cratering. Single family home sales were down (-33.4%) and condos are down (up 23.7%) compared to April 2017. Last year was a banner year though, so the pullback just gets us to historical norms. Inventory is starting to build, so the increase in housing availability is not limited to the rental market. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tom Davidoff, a professor in economics at UBC, is getting &lt;a href="https://globalnews.ca/news/4186361/thomas-davidoff-ubc-protesters-shaughnessy/"&gt;some heat&lt;/a&gt; from Shaughnessy homeowners for supporting the school tax. These protesters complained to UBC. Thankfully, UBC did the right thing and defended professor Davidoff's academic freedom. A statement from UBC reads, "Calls to interfere with the communication of scholarly opinions amount to a request to violate University policy. Respectfully, we cannot accede to such requests". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kathy Tomlinson dug up the (paywall warning) &lt;a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/article-flipping-of-condo-units-by-insiders-fuels-hot-vancouver-market/"&gt; flipping&lt;/a&gt; of condo units by developer insiders. While probably not the sole cause of price escalation, this does contribute to the feeling that the housing market is a rigged game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thestar.com/vancouver/2018/04/11/vancouver-makes-data-collection-deal-with-airbnb-in-effort-to-return-housing-to-rental-market.html"&gt;AirBnB has agreed&lt;/a&gt; to help Vancouver enforce short-term rental laws. Homeowners now need a business license and can face steep fines for nocompliance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://business.financialpost.com/news/fp-street/toronto-dominions-rivals-employ-gamesmanship-with-rate-hikes"&gt;Big banks are raising mortgage rates&lt;/a&gt;. TD now stands at 5.54% for a five year fixed mortgage. At this rate, it will take a few years to get back to pre-financial crisis territory of ~7%. Mortgage rates generally move in the opposite direction of housing prices, so this is yet another factor weighing on housing prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon &lt;a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/british-columbia/article-amazon-to-open-new-vancouver-office-create-3000-jobs/"&gt;announced it's intent to hire 3,000 new tech workers&lt;/a&gt; in the downtown area. The company aims to fill these positions by 2022. These highly paid workers will, no doubt, be looking for housing close by. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;April Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prices&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1695 (+4.3%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1950 (-1.5%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2700 (+0.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3000 (0.0%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volumes are down 4.8% from March, but up 12.8% YoY. Our 3 month moving average shows that volumes have steadily increased since July last year. We have more rental units available now than at any point last year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year-Over-Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I mentioned last month, there was a structural shift in rental prices last July. We are still seeing these large YoY gains, with prices up between 5% and 9% from last April. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2018&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1550&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1695&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%9.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1850&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1950&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%5.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2700&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%8.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2750&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%7.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Furnished&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the premiums for furnishing a unit: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median Unfurnished&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median Furnished&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Premium&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1580&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%26.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1850&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2400&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%29.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2495&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3495&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%40.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2790&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$4498&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%61.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/april-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/april-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/april-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/april-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - March 2018</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-march-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2018-04-11:monthly-rental-report-march-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;March Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a consistent uptick in rental volumes since last year. In March, we saw 5520 listings which is 26.9% more listings than last March. This marks 3 consecutive months of higher YoY listings. Year-to-date we recorded 16,115 listings versus 14,000 for the same period in 2017, a 15% increase. I am cautiously optimistic that newly introduced measures like the Empty Homes Tax are driving more rental stock. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices were a mixed bag. Studios and 2 bedrooms saw slight moderation while 1 bedrooms and 3 bedrooms saw some growth in rental pricing. The good news is we are still off from the high water mark of $2000 for a single bedroom seen last September. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1624.50 (-1.5%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1980 (+1.5%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2695 (-0.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3000 (3.4%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year-Over-Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One bedrooms saw a large year-over-year price surge of almost 9%. There appears to have been a structural change in the rental market in the summer of 2017. For 1 BRs, median prices escalated from  $1850 to $2000, and these prices have been stubbornly sticky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2018&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1570&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1624.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%3.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1820&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1980&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%8.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2695&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%3.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2750&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%9.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Furnished&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Jens heckling, I've finally split out the furnished and unfurnished listings. The results are pretty shocking, at least to me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The median price of a furnished unit offers at least a 30% premium to its unfurnished counterpart. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median Unfurnished&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median Furnished&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Premium&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%33.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1850&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2400&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%29.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2495&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3495&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%40.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2700&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$5112.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%89.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coincidentally, furnished units make up about 30% of the listings. This tails off as we get to the higher bedroom counts though. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Unfurnished Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Furnished Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Furnished&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;181&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%34.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1687&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;775&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%31.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1479&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;571&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%27.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;374&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;106&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%22.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/march-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/march-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/march-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/march-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Case Studies in Renting Versus Buying</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/case-studies-in-renting-versus-buying.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-03-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2018-03-11:case-studies-in-renting-versus-buying.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"You should buy because renting is paying someone else's mortgage."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've all gotten this advice. And, like most unsolicited advice, it's wrong. Reality is messy, and many factors affect the outcome of a real estate purchase. In this post, I want to unpack why this claim is overly simplistic by looking directly at the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After running the numbers for three typical units across the Lower Mainland, we found renting and buying produce qualitatively similar results. After 25 years, both renting and owning leave you in very comparable situations. If the future looks similar to our recent past, owning has a slight edge over renting. This advantage comes from the leveraged growth of taking out a mortgage at historically low rates. Owning a home is more a forced savings plan than a get-rich-quick scheme.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this comparison, we found three units with both rental and sales listings. For each unit, we first tally up the costs of both owning and renting. Then, we use these numbers to simulate two parallel universes in the computer; one each for renting and owning. Finally, we "fast-forward" 25 years to see who comes out financially ahead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK. On to the gory details. Let's start our analysis with the costs side of the equation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tallying Up Renting and Ownership Costs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will define a cost as anything that you pay and disappears afterwards. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of renting is clear. Every month you pay $X to occupy that housing unit. When the month is over, you don't own anything. The money you handed over was in exchange for the shelter received. That's basically it for the rental side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The costs of owning are more complicated because they are sprinkled around. First the obvious stuff: property taxes, insurance and maintenance. These costs go towards the city, and towards keeping your home in a livable state. They are similar to rent because you're just paying to occupy the unit. You don't get anything extra for paying these costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For owning costs, the mortgage payment is trickier. A mortgage is a savings plan and a loan rolled into one. Each month, part of your mortgage payment goes towards paying down capital, while the rest goes towards interest. You are paying this interest to the bank for borrowing their money. At the end of your term, you keep the capital, in the form of a house, but the interest disappears. Thus, the interest portion of the payment must be considered part of the cost of ownership. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, there are non-recoverable costs associated with both renting and owning. When renting, you pay the whole amount to your landlord every month. When buying, you pay maintenance, property taxes, insurance and interest to the bank. Since the market (i.e what other landlords are listing units for) determines rent, it's possible that owners are paying more in costs than they are receiving in rent. Which side "wins" is not immediately obvious. To get a better understanding, let's take a look at three case studies pulled from our data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Three Case Studies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes and Assumptions&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dollar values are not adjusted for inflation. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where I couldn't find the exact numbers, I estimated to the best of my abilities. These are clearly marked. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In both buy and rent scenarios we have saved 20% of the purchase price. The renter invests the down payment and any difference into a a stock market index fund like the S&amp;amp;P 500. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stock market average yearly return is 8% not adjusted for inflation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real estate average yearly returns are 3.9%, 4.6% and 6.7% for apartment, townhouse and detached respectively. These are the median real estate returns for the period of 2005-2017. See &lt;em&gt;Appendix&lt;/em&gt; for more details. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rent, property taxes and maintenance grow at inflation. Mortgage payments are constant. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comparison #1 - Condo In Downtown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Property Details&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;550 Square Feet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 Bedroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rent&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1600 / month [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8% average investment growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$600,000 purchase price [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$285 / month strata fee [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.39% Mortgage rate [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1423 Property Tax (2016) [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.9% average real estate growth rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Starting Monthly Payment (mortgage + taxes + maintenance):&lt;/em&gt; $2,778&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rent-versus-buy-post_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comparison #2 - Townhouse Near Metrotown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stats&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1300 Square Feet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Bedrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.5 Bathrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rent&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$2800 / month [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8% average investment growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$988,000 purchase price [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$557 / month strata fee [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.39% Mortgage rate [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1,884 Property Tax (2016) [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average growth rate of 4.6% [estimated]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Starting Monthly Payment (mortgage + taxes + maintenance):&lt;/em&gt; $4,628&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!--
Townhouse in Metrotown. 
{"link": "https://vancouver.craigslist.ca/van/apa/d/vancouver-brand-new-townhouse/6336064974.html", "baths": "2.5", "size": "1300", "price": "2800", "title": "Vancouver- Brand New Townhouse 3br near metrotown Available Now", "date": "2017-10-06 21:18", "longitude": -123.023604, "latitude": 49.232351, "beds": "3", "craigId": 6336064974}

Link: https://www.zolo.ca/vancouver-real-estate/5530-ormidale-street
5530-ormidale-street - 3BR, 2.5 Bath, Taxes: 1884.11, Fees: 557.22 / mnth, SqFt: 1300, Price: $988,800
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rent-versus-buy-post_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comparison Study #3 - Single Family Home On Dunbar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Property Details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2,683 Square Feet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 Bedrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 Bathrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rent&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$5380 / month [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8% average investment growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$3,388,000 purchase price [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$2,823 / month maintenance average [estimated at 1% of house value]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.39% Mortgage rate [listed]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$10,427 Property Tax [average 2016/2017] &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average growth rate of 6.7%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Starting Monthly Payment (mortgage + taxes + maintenance):&lt;/em&gt; $17,101&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!--
Property Tax 2017: 2.55489 * 3,650,000 / 1000 = $9300
Property Tax 2016: 3.16567 * 3,650,000 / 1000 = $11554
Average: $10,427

3493 W.20th Avenue
Price: 3,388,000
Rent: $5380

5 Beds | 5 Baths | 2,683 sq  | House |
2011 built | 3,794 lot sq 

Estimating home maintnance to be between $5000 and $10000 / year. Set to midpoint.
Source: https://www.theglobeandmail.com/globe-investor/personal-finance/household-finances/dont-let-home-maintenance-costs-crush-your-budget/article618105/?arc404=true
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rent-versus-buy-post_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rent-versus-buy-post_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Unit Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Buy Result&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Rent Result&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Diff&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Condo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.56M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.55M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%0.94&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Townhouse&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3.04M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.4M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%25.84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Single Family&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$17.14M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$14.5M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%17.81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 25 years, the financial positions of the renter and owner are roughly comparable. While the owner comes out ahead in all three scenarios, the largest gap is a 25% difference. Contrary to the mantra about throwing money away, the renter is not left empty-handed. At current price/rent levels, purchasing a condo appears to offer no benefits. Purchasing a townhome or detached home does result in a better outcome, but it takes over 15 years before owning pays off. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barring exceptional foresight into when to buy or sell, the contrast between buying and investing isn't drastic; a difference in degree, rather than a difference in kind. The last few years has seen exceptional housing appreciation, and I see some significant headwind to RE growth in the near future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big reason why buying comes out ahead in the last two cases is leverage. When you buy, you're effectively borrowing a huge chunk of money to bet on real estate. If your purchase appreciates, then your gain is amplified. Leverage can be similarly used to amplify your gains on the stock market. The difference is that a bank will loan you 4x your money to buy real estate, but no where close to that for buying stocks. Be careful though, the amplification applies to both gains and losses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think my numbers are unrealistic, try plugging in your own. I've linked to two different calculators in the resources section. Try the Holy Potato calculator if you're into spreadsheets. If not, the New York Times calculator is much more visual.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt; - If you're on the fence about renting or buying, flip a coin. Financially, it doesn't matter too much which way you go. Just make sure to invest the difference if you're a renter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Stephan Punwasi, Lara Thompson, Kiri Nichol, Ben Rabidoux, and John Robertson for their feedback on drafts of this post.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much digital ink has been spilled for this rent-versus-buy debate. Here are a few links that I found helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.holypotato.net/?p=1909"&gt;Holy Potato&lt;/a&gt; discusses the rent-versus-buy, also focusing on the Canadian market. He covers extensively covers the factors that go into both sides of the equation. His post also comes with a &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/14KJe4bprkDhT_fQjUxc5FhZmd2JdTXskBuGmS--F0FQ/edit"&gt;spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; that lets you play with different future scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/upshot/buy-rent-calculator.html"&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt; has an amazing visualization that shows you the impact of different factors on rent-versus-buy. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/bc/news/bc-120315-vancouver-renting-buying-analysis.pdf"&gt;CBC&lt;/a&gt; carried out a similar rent-vs-buy analysis for a Gastown condo in 2012. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you'd like to peek at the code, I've posted it all on &lt;a href="https://github.com/louiedinh/data-analyses/blob/master/vancouver-cl-rentals/Rent-Vs-Buy/case-studies-post-with-grant.Rmd"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Appendix&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Prediction is very difficult, especially about the future." -Niels Bohr&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An accurate rate of future real estate price growth is key to our rent-versus-buy comparison. It is also probably the hardest thing to nail down. In this article I used historical price growth between 2005 and 2016 to project forward. The hope is that the future looks approximately like the past. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a proxy for price growth, I used the &lt;a href="https://www.crea.ca/housing-market-stats/mls-home-price-index/hpi-tool/"&gt;HPI&lt;/a&gt; for Greater Vancouver. 
For the period of 2005-2016, price growth was highly related to year bought. The graph below shows the &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/cagr.asp"&gt;compounded-annual-growth-rate&lt;/a&gt;, by year bought and sold. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rent-versus-buy-post_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we assume that people buy when they have saved a sufficient down payment, rather than timing for a dip in the market, then the return profile will be similar to randomly sampling the start year. Similarly, let's just assume people sell in a random year when they hit retirement. We just take these CAGRs and use the median as our future growth rates. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is 6.69%, 4.63%, 3.9% for a single family home, town house and condo respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - January 2018</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-january-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-02-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2018-02-04:monthly-rental-report-january-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;January Real Estate Happenings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coming of the new year brought with it the universal mortgage stress test. This is a significant change to the Canadian real estate market. Starting January 1st, all mortgage applicants will have to qualify at the greater of the contract rate plus two percent, or the Bank of Canada's 5 year benchmark. This means many people will be forced to buy less house than before. Our government must be growing concerned with how much we are borrowing to buy housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More locally, the empty homes tax deadline is now past. As of January 29th, there were still 11% of homes that without a declaration. Owners that leave their property vacant face a stiff 1% tax on the assessed valume of the home. It's a bit too early to tell if the EHT is working, but so far the data is encouraging. Our numbers show that January set a record for number of listings recorded to date. The new year usually brings a surge in listings, but this month we saw ~15% more listings than our previous record. If this increased supply also drives prices down over a few months, then I'd chalk that up as win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, on to the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;January Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volumes surged 22.78% from December, and now sits at 5718 listings. This is much higher than the number of listings last January (5068). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices are flat across all unit types except 1 BR. Here are the prices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1600 (0.0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1950 (2.63%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2650 (0.0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3000 (0.0%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year-Over-Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Year-over-year change saw a large surge in 1 BRs. This is partly due to a dip in 1 BR prices last January. All other unit types are below the mandated cap of 4%. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2016&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1550&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%3.23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1800&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1900&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%8.33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2650&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%1.90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2900&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%3.45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/january-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/january-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/january-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/january-2018-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - December 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-december-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-01-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2018-01-09:monthly-rental-report-december-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Yearly Trend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;December was a quiet month in terms of housing. Instead of the usual blurb, I want to make observations about three broad trends  in the 2017 QR data in 2017. Let's see if these trends extrapolate into 2018. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rental market in 2017 was cyclical. Rental volumes started high in January, slowly tightened up between March and July, and then finished with rising volumes towards the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In tandem with (1), prices also appear cyclical. The price rise lags the lowered volume by a few months though. Prices start rising around June, and peak in September.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, rents are not skyrocketing. Year-over-year price increases have been in line with inflation. In fact, non-studio market rents have grown less than the legistlated cap of 3.7%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;December Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;December was a sleepy month for rental listings. Volumes are down 8% from the November surge in listings. Prices are all basically flat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1600 (-0.63%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1900 (0.0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2650 (0.0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3000 (0.0%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year-Over-Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, year-over-year rental increases are in line with inflation. Surprisingly, the median rent for 2 bedroom units became slightly cheaper YoY. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2016&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1525&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%4.90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1850&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1900&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%2.70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2700&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2650&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-%1.90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2925&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%2.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for December and Happy Belated New Year! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/december-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/december-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/december-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/december-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - November 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-november-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-12-03:monthly-rental-report-november-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;November Real Estate Happenings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November was the month of housing strategies. In an unusually coordinated fashion, all three levels of government are staking out their positions on the housing portfolio. Vancouver and Ottawa have released official housing strategies while the BC government is promising more details in their February budget. I'm only going to talk about the CoV strategy today. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The City of Vancouver has adopted a &lt;a href="http://council.vancouver.ca/20171128/documents/rr1appendixa.pdf"&gt;Housing Strategy&lt;/a&gt; for the next 10 years. Several people, like &lt;a href="https://www.gensqueeze.ca/tell_vancouver_city_council_you_support_the_new_housing_plan_but_need_some_specificity"&gt;Paul Kershaw&lt;/a&gt; (Generation Squeeze) and &lt;a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/opinion/housing-vancouver-strategy-i-want-to-believe-in-miracles/article37169583/"&gt;Steve Quinn&lt;/a&gt; (CBC), have expressed cautious optimism. I'm in agreement. The plan has a lot going for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the plan, The CoV finally recognizes that housing prices are an issue for the majority of Vancouverites. This is a shift from their previous focus on assisting only the most economically marginalized. The plan has details on how to address both the demand and supply sides of the housing equation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the demand side, speculation is acknowledged as a major driver. The plan has three planks for addressing demand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taxes and other policies that encourage living in the homes. Examples include the empty homes tax and the AirBnB regulations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarify land use policy that discourages land speculation and stablizes price growths going forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gather more data to understand where demand is coming from. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third point is promising. We like to blame foreign money but it's hard to know the breakdown of foreign versus local money. A recent article over at &lt;a href="https://betterdwelling.com/so-are-we-talking-about-these-canadian-cities-where-multiple-mortgages-are-rising/"&gt;Better Dwelling&lt;/a&gt; points to a big rise in second mortgages in Vancouver. One possibility is existing owners withdrawing equity to put a down payment on a second unit. Without peeking at the true ownership data, it's hard to know how much speculative demand is our own fault. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the supply side, the city is pushing some fairly aggressive ideas and targets. The best ones, in my opinion, are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allowing the densification of single family home neighbhourhoods. We are finally going to stop housing 35% of our population 80% of our land. &lt;a href="https://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/"&gt;Source: Mountain Math&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;62,000 new units for households making less than $80,000 per year. For reference, there were 309,418  units in the City of Vancouver according to the 2016 census. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempting to create "Rental Only Zones". This would help provide security of tenure, one of the oft cited benefits of owning, to the the city's renting population. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact, I was shocked to find out that 53% of the city's population is renting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK enough with the chatter, stats here we come!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;November Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices are down again in November and listing volumes have picked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volumes are up 4.18% month-over-month in November to 5078 listings. Marpole and Sunset saw a -3% tightening in listings, but all other major neighbhourhoods got more supply (Downtown +3.8%, Mount Pleasant +7% and Point Grey 6%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Median prices are also moderating along with the increased volume. Studios are roughly the same at $1590 versus $1600 last month. One bedrooms and two bedrooms are down $50 a piece to $1900 and $2650 respectively. Three bedrooms are up a sliver to $3000 though. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1590 (-0.63%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1900 (-2.6%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2650 (-1.8%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3000 (+0.20%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year-Over-Year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November is a big month because we finally have year-over-year data! In general, rental costs have gone up between 2% and 3% depending on the number of bedrooms. Studios were an outlier with a 6% increase, possibly due to newer units coming online. Remember those panic-inducing rental increases over the summer that drove one-bedrooms median rents to $2000? It looks like they were seasonal. Whew. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Beds&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2016&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median 2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pct Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1590&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%6.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1850&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1900&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%2.70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2650&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%1.92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2925&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$3000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;%2.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for November. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/november-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/november-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/november-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/november-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - October 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-october-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-10-31:monthly-rental-report-october-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!-- Tag URLS! --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MISSING DATA WARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: Due to the missing data last month, we do not look at rental volumes in September. I do include September for the median price analysis though. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;October Real Estate Happenings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, congratulations to Hector Bremner for winning the city by-election. He ran on a &lt;a href="http://hectorbremner.com/housing/"&gt;strong housing platform of increasing density across the city&lt;/a&gt;. Let's see if he can follow through. Gregor must be sweating at night thinking about next year's election. I have nothing against bike lanes, but &lt;a href="https://thinkpol.ca/2017/10/31/city-of-vancouver-resumes-accepting-vistro11s-complaints-following-outcry/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/business/cmhc-housing-outlook-1.4373251"&gt;housing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.vancourier.com/opinion/vancouver-development-community-shocked-by-new-normal-in-real-estate-prices-1.23074903"&gt;problem&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href="https://globalnews.ca/news/3827172/metro-vancouver-rent-census/"&gt;getting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/vancouver-strata-lawyer-preparing-class-action-lawsuit-against-airbnb-1.4368283"&gt;ridiculous&lt;/a&gt;. Thankfully (?) the problem has gotten so bad that &lt;a href="http://theprovince.com/news/local-news/ryan-holmes-hootsuite-ceo-without-affordable-housing-vancouver-risks-becoming-an-economic-ghost-town"&gt;companies started complaining about loss of talent&lt;/a&gt;. That ought to light a fire under their butts.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of winning elections based on housing policy, the NDP have &lt;a href="https://news.gov.bc.ca/releases/2017MAH0010-001815"&gt;drafted&lt;/a&gt; a much needed change to the yearly lease loophole. This change targets owners abusing a vacate clause in rental legislation to circumvent the maximum rental increase of inflation plus two percent. The exact number of directly affected tenants is unclear. However, its existence adds to the psychological angst of renting and encourages buying in this &lt;a href="https://betterdwelling.com/us-federal-reserve-indicator-shows-canadian-real-estate-is-way-overpriced/"&gt;overvalued market&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people, especially folks on &lt;a href="https://wwww.reddit.com/r/vancouver/"&gt;/r/vancouver&lt;/a&gt;, are getting impatient with the NDP. Personally, I'm waiting until February when the government delivers their full budget. I hope John Horgan knows that inaction on the housing file guarantees the NDP a spot on the opposition bench for another couple of decades. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the OSFI's &lt;a href="http://www.osfi-bsif.gc.ca/Eng/osfi-bsif/med/Pages/b20_dft_nr.aspx"&gt;stress testing guidelines&lt;/a&gt; have been released. Everyone applying for a mortgage must be eligible under the contracted mortgage rate plus two percent or the five year benchmark rate, whichever is greater. Back of the envelope calculations show that this change will reduce a household's purchasing power by up to 18%. Predicting the future is tough, but I'll stick out my neck and say that this certainly won't help price appreciation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK. Enough rambling. Onto the stats! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;October Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will compare against August because of the missing September data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of listings in October was robust. There were 4874 listings, close to our high water mark for the summer. Growth was very spikey however. Downtown listings grew by 12%, but the other major neighbhourhoods declined. Mount Pleasant (East) actually saw a volume decline of 17%. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My working theory is that students and summer visitors are leaving. Since visitors are overwhelmingly located in downtown, we would see volumes increase. The rest of the city is less affected by this trend, and would continue to see tightening. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time in a long time, we have price moderation. This would be consistent with the outflow of visitors in the more expensive core areas. Since these units are more pricey, the extra volume would cause landlords to ease up on their asking prices. I heard some rumbling of having to lower rents on Twitter, but it's nice that our data confirms it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1600 (-3%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1950 (-2.5%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2700 (-1.8%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $2950 (-0.2%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for October. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/october-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/october-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like there isn't much pattern in the growth of listings within a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/october-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/october-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - September 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-september-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-10-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-10-04:monthly-rental-report-september-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MISSING DATA WARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: My scraper was broken from September 19th until the end of the month due to some Craigslist website shuffling. I've compared against a few other sources, and the price measures are pretty consistent. I will not post the neighbhourhood breakdowns because of small samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;September Real Estate Happenings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On September 6th, the Bank of Canada pulled the trigger, raising interest rates to a whopping 1%. People who have fixed mortgages won't feel anything until renewal, but variable rates have been affected. This boost also affects the 1.9M Canadians borrowing against their homes through HELOCs. It's not so bad though, considering that a .25% increase in interest rates results in only an extra $167 in interest payments for the average HELOC amount ($67,000).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In BC, our housing minister, as her first act, has strengthened the Residential Tenancy Branch (RTB) with additional funding. The RTB will receive an additional $7 million over the next three years. This funding will be used, in part, to open up 26 new positions; the most exciting being a position for innovation! There are also talks of "imminent" legislation aimed at closing the 1-year lease loophole allowing land lords to keep resetting rents to market rates. These are all small steps in the right direction, and I look forward to their full budget next February. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I came across an &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@andersem/a-guy-just-transcribed-30-years-of-for-rent-ads-heres-what-it-taught-us-about-sf-housing-prices-bd61fd0e4ef9"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about predicting rental prices in San Francisco. Eric Fisher, a resident of SF, tabulated rental prices in the city back to 1979. Then, he tried to find factors that could be used to predict rental prices. Apparently, rental prices can be accurately inferred from just 3 factors: the number of jobs, the number of existing units, and the local wages.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;September Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first 18 days of September, compared against the same period in other months, listings grew 54%. I'd be careful reading too much into this though due to data missing-ness. Volume growth is probably driven by turnover of yearly student leases. This turnover would also explain why there is no corresponding drop in price. In fact, rental prices are on their way up again as landlords keep testing what the markets will bear. Medians for one bedrooms broke the $2000 mark (+2.6% MoM), two bedrooms are now at $2750 (+5.8% MoM) and three bedrooms at $3000 (+1.7% MoM). Only studios have been stable at $1650. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1650 (+0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $2000 (+2.6%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2750 (+5.8%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $3000 (+1.7%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for September. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/september-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/september-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - August 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-august-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-09-01:monthly-rental-report-august-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;August Real Estate Happenings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new stress-test proposal from the Office of the Superintendent of Financial Institutions (OSFI) could rattle the housing market. The proposal is to stress test all uninsured mortgages at the quote plus two%. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a quick reminder, if your down payment is less than 20% then you need to insure your mortgage. If you can dig up 20%, then your mortgage is uninsured. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, OFSI introduced a similar stress-test but only on uninsured mortagages. Instead of cooling the housing market, the test &lt;a href="https://betterdwelling.com/canadian-uninsured-mortgages-hit-all-time-high-at-end-of-2016/"&gt;pushed buyers into uninsured mortgages&lt;/a&gt;. Typically, you can borrow money, from family or alternative lenders, to inch past the 20% mark. Voila, no stress-test. This time they are really bringing the hammer down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others have speculated that the main cause of our housing bubble woes is the abnormally low interest rates. A stress test would boost effective interest rates by 2% overnight. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make matter worse, an interest rate hike is looking increasingly likely. Canada's Q2 performance wow'ed economists, coming in at &lt;a href="http://business.financialpost.com/news/bank-of-canada-rate-hike-odds-rise-after-blistering-gdp-growth-wows-analysts"&gt;an annualized rate of 4.5%&lt;/a&gt;. Since the prices of homes are set by how much people can borrow, this could be a perfect storm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On to the rental stats now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;August Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August, listing volume across the city increased by 8%! There were almost 5000 listings in the month of August. This volume is probably because summer is ending, and people are all moving home. Just normal school year churn. Previously, only January saw more listing volume. Mt-Pleasant-E lead with +19% volume growth, while Downtown, Mt-Pleasant-W, Pt-Grey and Sunset all saw +10% volume growth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this volume isn't depressing prices much. Median rentals are a mixed bag (month over month changes in parentheses). We're about to break the $2000 mark for a one bedroom apartment in Vancouver though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1650 (+0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1950 (+2.6%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2600 (-1.8%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $2950 (+1.7%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for August. &lt;strong&gt;If you want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market, sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/august-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/august-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/august-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/august-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - July 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-july-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-08-04:monthly-rental-report-july-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since people are asking about good rental deals, I'm going to start sending them out weekly. To avoid flooding the listings, I will only be sending it to 100 people. If you're interested, please &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/di1oT4GQw2ukX1el2"&gt;fill out this form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;July Real Estate Happenings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PadMapper's &lt;a href="http://blog.padmapper.com/2017/07/17/july-2017-canadian-rent-report/"&gt;rental report&lt;/a&gt; about one bedrooms at $2090 has been getting attention lately. Single room suites breaking $2000 makes a good headline, but it was mostly scare mongering. Our numbers show that median rent for July was $1900, which is a modest increase of 2.7% over June. So while one bedroom rents did go up, it's not that bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-june-2017.html"&gt;last report&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the possibility of our central bank hiking interest rates. Well, it happened. On July 12th, Stephen Poloz &lt;a href="http://www.bankofcanada.ca/core-functions/monetary-policy/key-interest-rate/"&gt;pulled the trigger&lt;/a&gt; and rates are now at 0.75%. People are telling me that this is a return-to-normal. I wouldn't know though because, as a millennial, I've lived with emergency rates my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One consequence of higher rates is that banks will loan less money to people buying real estate. Since prices are set by how much people can borrow, we could see the cost of buying come down. If prices do moderate, we will have to reconsider the &lt;a href="http://www.canadamortgage.com/calculators/rentvsown.cgi"&gt;rent-or-own&lt;/a&gt; decision. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the political front, we got a new housing minister. In late June, the NDPs managed to vote the Liberals out of power. The new ruling party assigned BC's housing portfolio to Selina Robinson, a surpise pick over David Eby. The popular housing critic was instead appointed Attorney General.  Last we've heard, Robinson is currently reviewing all housing related measures&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;July Rental Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, listing volume across the city increased by 4.6%. Mt-Pleasant-W, (+8.7%), Marpole (4.7%), and Mt-Pleasant-E (+3.2%) led the charge in volume growth. Rental volumes in other neighbhourhoods were pretty much unchanged from last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Median rental prices are up for almost all segments (month over month changes in parentheses).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studios $1650 (+5.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bedrooms $1900 (+2.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 bedrooms $2650 (+3.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bedrooms $2900 (+0%) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know what the guys at StatsCan are doing, but they claim that inflation is sub 2%. This looks like inflation of housing costs to me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want to stay up-to-date on Vancouver's rental market? Sign up for my newsletter in the navigation bar.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/july-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/july-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/july-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/july-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - June 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-june-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-07-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-07-02:monthly-rental-report-june-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;June was an exciting case study of policy affecting real estate. Currently, plans at all three levels of government could cause ripples in our rental data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federally, recent statements from the Bank of Canada signal their intention to slowly back away from emergency interest rates. At Trois-Rivières, senior deputy governor Wilkins &lt;a href="http://www.bankofcanada.ca/2016/10/economic-trends-monetary-policy/"&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; oil revenue isn't doing so hot, but the non-resource economy has been growing steadily. This was supported by a &lt;a href="http://www.statcan.gc.ca/daily-quotidien/170609/dq170609a-eng.htm?HPA=1&amp;amp;indid=3587-2&amp;amp;indgeo=0"&gt;surprisingly large increase in full time employment&lt;/a&gt; (+77,000) and increasingly positive business outlook. In Portugal, BoC governer Poloz said that low rates have "done their job". A rate hike means higher mortgage costs which usually means lower housing prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in BC, Christie Clark is still putting up a fight. The latest proposed house-price-inflating measure is a rent-to-own system released with the &lt;a href="http://www.rew.ca/news/bc-liberals-announce-rent-to-own-housing-scheme-1.20724004"&gt;throne speeech on June 22nd&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is to create 50,000 units in partnership with the private sector. We don't know any particulars but the idea exists elsewhere. Generally, a renter, after a fixed lease, has the option to purchase the home. Once again, the Liberals are covertly pushing the idea that renting is "flushing your money down the toilet". You don't need to pay attention though because NDP/Greens have given Christie the boot and taking a shot at governing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Gil Kelly our new planner from down south, delivered a &lt;a href="http://council.vancouver.ca/20170628/documents/pspc6.pdf"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; to the City about our empty homes problem. Apparently the census last year found approximately 25,000 dwellings (8.2% of our stock) that were unoccupied or occupied by temporary residents. Similar census counts from 2001 shows that this has grown from ~13,000 (+5.2%). The report explicitly recommends against any exceptions for second homes, or houses on the market. If deemed empty, the owner forks up a hefty 1% of the assessed value per year. The deadline to rent out a dwelling and avoid the tax is July 1st. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the new tax did not result in an uptick in rental inventory across the city. I guess some owners will just cough up the empty homes tax. The rest have probably listed earlier in the year, explaining the huge spike in volume we saw in January. In June, listing volume across the city dropped 2%. Sunset (+28%) and Marpole (+17%) saw large increases, but this was offset by fewer listings in Downtown (-5%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the price side, the market seems to be split in two. Family units (2+ bedrooms) are seeing price appreciation while the one bedrooms and studios have not. In fact, studios (-2.5%) saw a dip in median rent for the month of June and go for $1560. Median rent for 2 bedrooms is now at $2550 (+2%) and 3 bedrooms goes for $2900 (+1.75%). One bedrooms had no change in price, with median rents still at $1850.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/june-2017-rental-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Monthly Rental Report - May 2017</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/monthly-rental-report-may-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-06-20:monthly-rental-report-may-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the third post analyzing rental postings in Vancouver. Here are links to the &lt;a href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/vancouver-rental-landscape.html"&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/rentals-go-fast-and-its-expensive-to-live-downtown.html"&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; posts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We expect some &lt;a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/british-columbia/ndp-greens-seek-ways-to-cool-british-columbias-housing-market/article35185394/"&gt;new measures aimed at cooling the housing market&lt;/a&gt; if the NDP and Greens sucessfully form government. Wouldn't it be great to see if anything is working? Ideally, we would look at housing sale prices but the released aggregates are &lt;a href="https://betterdwelling.com/city/vancouver/the-canadian-government-thinks-vancouver-homes-are-cheaper-than-in-2008-seriously/"&gt;clear as mud&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, let's use our rental data as a proxy. Since changes in buying sentiment shifts the rent vs. buy equation, we should be able to observe effects indirectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, we have to start recording data now to serve as a baseline. So, I'm going to start writing these rental reports on a monthly basis. Each report will summarize that month's data along with comparisons to the historical trend. Ready? Let's go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the month of May, we saw rental volumes pulling back slightly (-3%) across the city. Decreasing volume was mainly driven by lower supply in Sunset and Marpole. In the other 4 rent-dense areas (Downtown, Mount-Pleasant-E/W, and Point Grey) volumes have been stable MoM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the price front, the median cost of rentals have been stable for 1 ($1850) and 2 ($2500) bedrooms. However, prices for Studios (+3.22%) and 3 bedrooms (+1.78%) have risen slightly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, despite all the sales news, the rental situation in Vancouver has stayed mostly the same in the last few months. Is this the calm before the storm?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/monthly-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/monthly-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/monthly-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/monthly-report_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Rentals Go Fast and It's Expensive To Live Downtown</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/rentals-go-fast-and-its-expensive-to-live-downtown.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-05-26:rentals-go-fast-and-its-expensive-to-live-downtown.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the second post about the rental market in Vancouver. The initial post on Vancouver's rental market can be found &lt;a href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/vancouver-rental-landscape.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s face it, renting in Vancouver isn’t easy. The prices are high and the competition is stiff. Rumor has it that no one can find pet-friendly housing and if you do luck out, you’ll get renovicted in a few months anyways. Just the thought of having to move sends me into a sweaty panic. But are we stressed out with good reason? How bad is it really? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad news first. Rents are indeed increasing and most listed units are gone within the week. This is from looking at rental postings on CL for the last 6 months. But things are not all bad. The price increases are uneven across the city, and smaller units are slightly easier to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rent Increases Have Been Localized to Downtown.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking across the city rents have been pretty consistent since December 2016. One bedroom price changes are hovering around 0, while two bedrooms swing but in both directions. Downtown is the outlier, with rents increasing every month since last December. The median one bedroom in Downtown now costs north of $2000. Padmapper found similar numbers in their recent &lt;a href="http://blog.padmapper.com/2017/05/16/2017-may-rent-report-canada/"&gt;rental report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you’re apartment hunting, try looking around the city instead. In four of the five most rental-dense neighbourhoods, rents rose towards the end of the year but then quickly moderated into January and February. Though more recently, prices have ticked up between 5% and 10%. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/median-rents-overall-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/median-rent-by-nbhd-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/median-rent-change-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;If You Spot a Good Place, Act Fast.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because about half of all units disappear within just three days of listing.  Wait ten days and 80% of listings are gone. These numbers change a bit depending on the size and location though. Studios stay listed for a bit longer than one bedrooms, which last longer than 2 bedrooms. Also, it’s easier to find a listing in Downtown because you get about about 12 hours extra compared to Sunset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/city-wide-absorption-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/absorption-by-bed-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/absorption-by-nbhd-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/absorption-by-nbhd-zoom-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Waiting Doesn’t Work. Try Asking?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, about 15% of landlords &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; revise their prices and usually downwards. However, this is unrelated to the number of days the unit has been listed. Most discounts are within 10% of the original price. You’d think the owners would back down after a few weeks but alas, rental prices are sticky. You might have better luck appealing to their sentimental side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/price-change-scatter-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/pct-change-histogram-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/rentals-over-time_files/figure-html/against-dom-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Final Remarks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after looking at the data, we recommend the following course of action:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To find a good deal, try looking outside of downtown where prices have mostly been stable. If you really want to live in the heart of the city, be prepared to shell out especially for 2 or more bedrooms. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure to act fast. Most places are gone within a week of posting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waiting for a landlord to drop their prices doesn’t usually work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks of reading! Also, I'm currently available for both short and longer term opportunities related to data science. If you or someone you know is looking
for someone to make sense out of their data, drop me a line.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Vancouver Rental Landscape</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/vancouver-rental-landscape.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2017-03-03:vancouver-rental-landscape.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was born and raised in Vancouver and for as long as I can remember my mom has been nagging me to buy real estate. This is normal in Asian families. As a kid, I obviously couldn't afford it. Over time my earnings have grown along with my age but the sky rocketing prices leave real estate perpetually out of reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a housing hopeful, the news coverage is an emotional roller coaster. One day sales collapse and hope is restored, only to be followed by a surge that leaves prices at dizzying new heights. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of hard data was frustrating so I decided to do a little digging on my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular post explores the rental market in Vancouver. Sales numbers are exciting, but hard to compile and strongly affected by speculation. Rental prices are more stable and act as a proxy for demand of living space. We will be exploring where rentals are located within the city, and how much it will cost to rent in each neighbhourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My data source is a popular online rental marketplace. The data was retrieved between November 6th, 2016 and December 9th, 2016. After cleaning and removal of duplicates, the dataset contains 5138 listings in the city of Vancouver. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To aid this investigation, I arbitrarily split Vancouver into neighbhourhoods. The grid lines are eyeballed to approximate the neighbourhood boundaries and labeled with names off the top of my head. Please don't take them literally. I know they are wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my arbitrarily labelled map of Vancouver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/setup-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, where are all these rentals located? A quick plot shows us that rentals are not evenly spread across the city. Here each dot is a rental posting. There is a large concentration in Downtown and along the Broadway corridor between Arbutus and Nanaimo. The rest of Vancouver is sparse in terms of vacancies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/density-plot-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking this down further, we can see that Downtown 47%, Mt-Pleasant-W (9%) and Mt-Pleasant-E (5%) account for more than half of the rental stock. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/rental-dist-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although rentals in Downtown and along Broadway are abundant, they might not be ideal for families. Diving into the bedroom and square footage distributions, we notice that neighbourhoods can have very distinct rental stock profiles. Some neighbourhoods have many more 1 Bedroom units (BRs), than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/bedroom-dist-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High rental density areas probably correspond to higher density buildings like apartments. Notice that Downtown and Mt-Pleasant-E have very distinct staircase patterns in the bedroom distribution. Many one bedrooms, then less two bedrooms, etc. In older neighbourhoods, where we expect more single family dwellings, the pattern is different. We see many more dwellings with 2 or more BRs (e.g Renfrew, Sunset and Cambie). Also, there are some nice intermediate neighbourhoods where we see the two patterns mixing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to prove this is the case using our current dataset, but can probably be verified in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size distribution is not that exciting. As previously identified, the neighbourhoods show two distinct patterns, with some mixing. The size distribution follows a similar trend to our bedrooms. 
&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/size-dist-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/size-dist-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we look at the price distribution. Let's be honest, rent in Vancouver are not cheap. The most distinct pattern is the East/West divide. The median west side home is priced over $2000 for every neighbhourhood except Marpole. Conversely, none are over $2000 on the east side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common rule of thumb is that you can comfortably spend at most 33% of your income on housing costs. This works out to $72,000 take-home pay or $95,000 in gross salary. Of course, this is for median household, not just a single person. A newly graduated student living with a roommate would target a much different rental market than a 4 person family. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/price-dist-1.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/static/vancouver-rental-landscape_files/figure-html/price-dist-2.png" /&gt;&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even this high level view of the hard data allows us to draw some conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A large fraction of rentals (0.62) available in Vancouver are in Downtown and on the Broadway corridor between Nanaimo and Arbutus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two main neighbourhood patterns emerge: high density, small units with fewer bedrooms. Or low density, lots of bedrooms, and space. A few neighbourhoods are a mixture of these two patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rent on the east side is much cheaper than the west side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, we will explore the factors that lead to higher prices and what you can expect to rent for in each neigbhourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Charles, Mya, Maude, Ganesh, Simon and Gilbert for early comments and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>My Collection Of Notes</title><link href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/my-collection-of-notes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-03T10:20:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Louie Dinh</name></author><id>tag:quantitativerhetoric.com,2015-05-03:my-collection-of-notes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Misc. Notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://quantitativerhetoric.com/notes/logistic-regression.pdf"&gt;Logistic Regression Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>